Let's look at Android Startup Init process.
When we talk about any process, we must first look at the steps of Android system, startup process.
So here is a timeline diagram of Android boot process.
So in this diagram, the first step is the power on our own and system startup.
When the power is pressed, the boot type code starts executing from a predefined place.
And this is basically hardcoded in the ROM.
This loads the bootloader into the RAM and its accuracy.
So whenever we press the power button in a mobile device, it start it executing from a predefined address
which is hardcoded in the role.
And this will load the bootloader into the RAM and it gives it the bootloader.
It's a small program which runs before the operating system starts running.
Its main function is to start the system OS.
So in our case, this bootloader will start the Linux kernel.
So as we know, Android is based on Linux kernel.
So the bootloader is basically responsible for starting the Linux kernel.
So once the Linux kernel starts, it sets the affected memory cache and it loads all the system drivers
like the audio medial Catholic's drivers, all sorts of drivers.
When the kernel finishes setting up the system looks for the unique dot RC file, so there is a file
configuration file you need to file.
So it will look for any files in the system files and then it starts the root process for the first
process in the system, which is called the unit process.
So in this session, we are going to dig deeper into the unit process.
Okay.
We'll see what role actions are being performed in this process and we'll have a code walkthrough and
see which files or which modules are responsible for this init process.
In the later tutorials we will cover zygote system, server system, UI and launcher.
The init process mainly does four things.
So the first step is to create the folders and mount the device.
So in the first step, it basically creates the file system of Android.
In the second step, it creates the is SELinux policies.
So in case if you don't know what a c linux's is, Linux stands for security enhanced Linux A C.
Linux is a set of rules to improve the security of your system.
So I have created a different tutorial for Linux, so you will learn about that later.
So in the third step it will initialize and start the property.
Are we?
So Android maintains a set of properties.
It is very similar to the registry entry in Windows.
So you might have seen the registry in Windows eight where we have a property and Android also does
something very similar.
So in Android it is a set of properties which has a key value where property name and the value and
this property and value are used in a lot of places in Android.
By using ADB, we can get the list of these properties and their values.
I'll show you how to do that.
Then in the fourth step you pass the you need to RC configuration file and start the zygote process.
So we look out of the zygote process in a separate tutorial.
So in this tutorial you'll see how the zygote process is getting started.
Let's look at the modules which implements the INI process and Android so you can find most of the init
modules within this folder.
It is within a speech system goal you need.
I have a bookmark for the most important modules.
So here we have the main dose CBP, which consists of a main method.
Within this method, we could find three methods which are pretty important.
So the first one is must stage main.
The Foster State's main method is mainly responsible for creating the directories and mounting the devices.
So we can see that it's mainly mounting the devices and creating the directories here.
Second, we have the setup and SELinux method.
So within setup, a select method basically loads all the is seal index related policies and it sets
the enforcement of AC Linux and it said AC Linux enforcement as well.
So you learn in detail about AC Linux in a later tutorial.
But for now, just keep in mind that Linux is a set of rules to enhance the security of your system.
The third method within mean is second stage main.
So the second stage main is implemented in.
You need not simply be within any dot, simply be the main method which we need to look at is property
in it.
So the property basically initializes the properties within the system.
So in Android there are a lot of properties which are initiated at the startup.
So it is very similar to the Windows Registry property value path.
I'll show you how we can see the properties.
Let me open up the emulator.
So to see the properties which are initialized in the emulator, we need to go to the shell and it broke.
So this lists all the properties which are set within the system.
These properties are used in many places, so for example, are not built out.
So this is the product name of these.
You can see these in the settings.
If you go to settings, you can see many of these properties are listed here.
Like, for example, if you go to about emulator device.
So here you can see the build number, right?
So the build number is built from these build properties.
Okay.
So it's basically a concatenation of all these.
Similarly, all these properties are used in many, many places within the within the OS while booting
up and also after booting up it's used for many purposes even.
You can have a runtime reserves overlay based on these properties.
Okay.
So the property in it basically loads all the properties and then we have the init say good note rc
file.
So the INI process basically reads this RC file and it starts the zygote process.
So we need dot RC is a configuration file with scripts written in an android init language.
So it mainly consists of five types of statements, like some action statements, commands, services,
options and imports.
So it's a very simple language.
So you can Google it to find more information about this init language.
Okay.
So this unique dot RC file is actually passed by the passado prototype within the init folder and it
will start the zygote process.
So if you want to debug something in this init process, then you can always have a look at the logcat
for this tag.
So you need.
So all the.
Activities done in the unit will be tagged with this any time so you can search for this and find the
different tasks performed during that unit process.
Okay.
So I hope you have got a high level view of what's happening in the unit process.
Thank you.